NYSUT Vice-President's Office, Maria Neira Files. 6174/016
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- Executive Committee 1/28/05, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  Agenda; presidents' report; preliminary draft for internal use only, "Potential Impact of Changing Regents Passing for 55 to 65"; nominations for "Not for Ourselves Alone" Outstanding Leadership Award; list of NYSUT Constituency Award recipients; NYSUT Building Corporation Board of Directors agenda for January 28 meeting and minutes of December 10, 2004, meeting
- Executive Committee 12/10/04, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  Agenda; report and outline of oral report of first vice president; list of 2005 Field Service conferences; draft NYSUT policy statement on SED proposals to amend Commissioner's Regulations Section 52.21 related to full-time faculty staffing and workload requirements for teacher preparation programs, December 2004; educational issues briefing to NYSUT Board of Directors
- Executive Committee Video Conference 11/15/04, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  Memos from NYSUT president Tom Hobart re NYSUT/NEA unity, with attached document, "Fundamental Beliefs to Create a Single State Union," November 11, 2004
- Executive Committee 6/10/04, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  Agenda; report of first vice president; 2004-2005 budget presentation; report by executive vice president Alan Lubin
- Executive Committee 5/24/04, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  Agenda; minutes of April 15 video conference; report and outline of oral report of first vice president; addendum: NYSUT Reactions to the May 6, 2004, SED Middle-Level Proposal; text of proposal; financial statement as of April 30, 2004; brochure, "Teachers, Unions, and the Fight for Civil Rights"
- Executive Committee 4/15/04, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  Agenda; report of first vice president; membership and financial report from secretary- treasurer Ivan Tiger; "Middle-Level Talking Points," highlighting newest SED proposal; list of members of proposed task force on future of RAs
- Executive Committee 2/12/04, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  Report of first vice president; minutes of March 25, 2004, meeting; resolution submitted to the NYSUT Board of Directors, Care of Diabetic Children in Schools, calling for licensed registered nurse in every school; material re Regents Examination in Mathematics A; spreadsheet re NYSUT/LSA negotiations, tentative agreement
- Exemplar Todd Feigenbaum 11/17/05, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  Correspondence between Maria Neira and Feigenbaum, managing partner, Exemplar LLC, to arrange meeting, noting (USNY?) summit
- Expiring Resolutions, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  Several edited drafts of procedure for expiring resolutions
- Sandra Feldman Conference Calls 11/4/05, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  List of potential speakers; minutes of 10/28/05 planning meeting; draft of script for recorded outgoing message on RSVP phone line, 11/2/05, with handwritten list of conference call dates; notice of next planning meeting, with conference call information
- Field and Legal Services 12/8/04, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  Agenda; related memos
- Field and Legal Services Management 9/21/05, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 61)
  Agenda; handwritten notes
- Field and Legal Services Meeting 4/28/05, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 62)
- Field and Legal Services 3/3/05, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  Newspaper clippings, including op-ed from Schenectady Daily Gazette, "National teacher certification isn't worth it," March 2, 2005; presentation re Rochester Teachers Association Dial-a-Teacher tutoring program; Rochester City School District Supplemental Education Plan (SEP); handwritten notes from regional staff meeting
- Field and Legal Services Labor at the Crossroads Conference December 2-3, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 64)
  Conference agenda
- Field and Legal Services Legal Staff Meeting 11/22/04, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 65)
  Agenda of staff meeting
- Field and Legal Services Management Regional Staff Directors Retreat 11/9/04, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 66)
  A Guide to Field & Legal Services; agenda for retreat, November 8-10; list of discussion items for officers Tom Hobart, Dick Ianuzzi, Maria Neira
- Four-State Study on Improving College Readiness and Success, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 67)
  The Governance Divide: A Report on a Four-State Study on Improving College Readiness and Success, September 2005, by Institute for Educational Leadership, National Center for Public Policy and Higher Education, Stanford Institute for Higher Education Research
- Grow Network 3/3/04, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 68)
  Meeting agenda, March 3, 2004; presentation sheets, "AFT and Grow Network: Making Data Useful for Instruction"; newsletters/reports, including sample showing individualized 2004 standardized test results in NYC; folder packets
- Health and Safety Conference March 11-13, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 69)
  Tentative program; invitation to local presidents
- PFT Health and Welfare Fund February 25-26, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 70)
  Poster for "Programs for Teaching" conference sponsored by Philadelphia Federation of Teachers Health and Welfare Fund; agenda
- High School Focus Group 5/17/06, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 71)
  List of teachers, high school focus group participants; memos; handwritten notes
- High Schools PSA 4/26/06, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 72)
  List of high school focus group participants; memos; list of low-performing schools
- High-Tech High Schools 6/21/05, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 73)
  Correspondence re setting up meeting to discuss high-tech high schools, with handwritten notes
- Higher Education Council Meeting 9/30/05, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 74)
  Agenda; outline of introductory remarks, noting attendance by Deputy Commissioner of Education Johanna Duncan-Poitier
- Higher Education Council Meeting 4/7/05, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 75)
  Minutes of NYSUT Higher Education Council meeting of April 7; articles from Inside Higher Education: "Next Step for Higher Ed Act," September 9; "Rare Win for Private College Unions," "A Gag on Public Faculty?" "New Challenge to Evolution," August 29; "Calling Off Ann Coulter," September 1
- Higher Education Council Meeting January 7-8, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 76)
- Higher Education Council Meeting October 22-23, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 77)
  Agenda; list of members of council; draft Master Plan 2004- 2008, State University of New York; Master Plan 2004-2008, City University of New York; articles from Chronicle of Higher Education; correspondence from State Education Department
- Higher Education Database Project 5/12/05, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 78)
  Meeting agenda; statement of purpose; outlines of design team, finance elements, characteristics of students and faculty; charts showing changes in state and local share of school revenues, 1982-2004, annual change in state aid, 1990-2005; school aid in the 2005-06 legislative budget; School District/ Community Special Information Packet: Newark, for Rochester Regional Office Negotiations Workshop, January 2005
- Higher Education Full-Time Faculty Policy Modification 2005 (Box 3, Folder 79)
  Correspondence between NYSUT vice president Maria Neira and Education Deputy Commissioner Poitier re change in Commissioner's Regulations re full-time faculty requirements for accreditation of institutions of higher learning for education programs
- Higher Education Lobby Day February 28-March 1, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 80)
- Hispanic Affairs Committee (HAC) Gala (UFT) 1/26/05, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 81)
  Invitation and correspondence; handwritten notes for remarks; newspaper clipping (opinion column re teacher pay); tickets to event; memorabilia; letter to Randi Weingarten, president, UFT, from Puerto Rican Legal Defense and Education Fund re annual awards gala, November 17, 2004
- HAC Gala Event 11/30/04, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 82)
  Program; handwritten notes for remarks; related correspondence
- HAC/Somos El Futuro, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 83)
  List of contacts
- 2005 Hispanic Heritage Month (Box 3, Folder 84)
  Census facts; list of events
- Hispanic Caucus, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 85)
  Top 3 Policy Recommendations from 2004 Issues Conference
- NYSUT History Project, 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 86)
  Letter from NYSUT president Tom Hobart to vice president Antonia Cortese re NYSUT history project, with attached questions for oral history interview, developed by interns, November 1, 1989; follow-up letter from Hobart admitting to not reading the questions thoroughly, noting that questions re 1978 convention were inappropriate and would not be included, November 2; Outline for Video History of New York State United Teachers, covering period 1960-71, discussing issues re merger between NYSTA and United Teachers of New York; brochure, "We Are the People Who Help New York to Learn" April 1990
- Holiday/ Solidarity Reception 12/3/04, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 87)
  Flyer for Holiday/Solidarity Reception at NYSUT Southwest Regional Office
- Independent Commission on Public Education (ICOPE), 2006 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  Documents, ICOPE's Vision and ICOPE Education Action Summit Platform: Building a Human Rights Vision for New York City Public Schools; list of Teachers of the Year, 1965-2006
- ING Life Insurance: Opportunity Plus, 2004-2005 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  Description of benefit for NYSUT members; letters to members from NYSUT president Richard Ianuzzi and benefits chair Ivan Tiger
- Inservice Meeting 5/12/05, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  Progress report for planned conference, tentatively planned for March 23-24, 2006
- In-Service Conference Debriefing 2/3/05, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  Conference Evaluation Report on 23rd Annual Statewide Conference on Inservice Education, October 23-24, 2004; debriefing reports from co-chairs, others; revenue and expense reports
- Inservice Conference 10/24-26/04, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  Program for 23rd Annual Statewide Conference on Inservice Education, "Strengthening Teaching and Learning"; talking points and text of remarks for Maria Neira, introducing keynote speaker, Dr. Terrence Roberts; biography of Dr. Roberts
- Job Training Improvement Act see AFT Job Training Improvement Act
- Just For The Kids 11/19/04, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  Letter to NYSUT president Tom Hobart from Susan D. Phillips, chair of Just For The KidsNew York (JFTK) and dean of the School of Education, SUNY University at Albany, inviting him to join Advisory Board of JFTK, describing program, October 20, 2004; handwritten note re conversation with Jeanette Angelo, SUNY Albany, November 3, 2004; memo from Phillips to Chuck Santelli, welcoming him to advisory board, November 10, 2004; memo from Phillips re high performing schools, with attached list, including racial and income demographics; minutes of Advisory Board meeting of 11/19/04
- James Kadamus Q and A Grades 3-8 Testing Program New York Teacher Article December 2005 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  Article by James Kadamus, State Education Department Deputy Commissioner for Elementary, Middle, Secondary, and Continuing Education; questions and answers re mathematics and English language arts test for grades 3-8. See also Mathematics Standards Committee (SED)
- Kerry/Bush Debate House Party 9/30/04, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  Memo to NYSUT Headquarters staff, Public Employees Federation, CSEA, and Capital District Area Labor Federation, from NYSUT executive director Alan Lubin, inviting them to party to view screening of film about Democratic presidential candidate and decorated Vietnam war hero, "Going Upriver: The Long War of John Kerry," attend dinner, and then watch the presidential debate between Kerry and incumbent president George W. Bush, September 20; save-the-date memo from Lubin to NYSUT headquarters staff re September 30 Kerry/Bush debate "house party," September 16. See also Post-Election Summary
- LM-2 Reporting, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  Memo from Maria Neira estimating percentage of time spent on U.S. Department of Labor categories (representational, political and lobbying, contributions, gifts, and grants, general overhead, and union administration), for annual LM-2 report, November 10, 2005
- Local Action Project (LAP), 2005 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  Presentation sheets, mostly photos, "Energizing Locals for Greater Success"
- LAP 2005 (2004 Conference Evaluations et al.), 2004-2005 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  Program for 2005 conference; evaluations; applications, with local information; letters to Hempstead Teachers Association and several other locals re acceptance in Local Action Project, May 9, 2005
- LAP Review of 2005 LAP Planning Conference 9/26/05 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  2005 NYSUT LAP Conference (July 18-21, 2005) Evaluations; Local Action Project 2005 program
- LAP Summer Planning Conference July 18-21, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  2005 Local Action Project Summer Planning Conference: Maria Neira's Opening Remarks (several drafts); introduction of Mark Richard by Maria Neira; program; related memos
- LAP Summer Planning Conference 7/14/05, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  Local Action Project Summer Planning Conference: Maria Neira's Opening Remarks
- LAP 2005 4/22/05 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  Notes on meeting of April 22; related memos
- LAP Budget Requests, 2006-2007 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  LAP budget requests for various locals, marked "Class of 2005," "Class of 2006," "Class of 2007"
- LAP Budget Meeting 10/31/05, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  Annual budget submission instructions; memo to LAP Committee re 2005-2006 grant requests, November 1, 2005
- LAP Budget Meeting 7/1/05, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  Instructions for annual budget submission; memos re meeting
- Local Presidents Conference Planning Committee Meeting 3/6/06, 2006 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  Pre-RA Local and Retiree Council Presidents' Conference meeting agenda, March 6, 2006; meeting minutes of January 27, 2006
- Local Presidents Conference Planning Committee Meeting 12/1/05, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  Local and Retiree Council Presidents' Conference program, May 3-4, 2006; meeting minutes of Pre-RA Local and Retiree Council Presidents' Conference planning meeting of October 4, 2005
- Local Presidents Conference Planning Committee Meeting 2006 Zoilo Rodriguez 10/4/05, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  Tentative schedule for Pre-RA Local and Retiree Council Presidents' Conference, April 6-7, 2005; program; meeting agenda of October 4, 2005; 2005 Local Presidents' Conference Evaluations; correspondence
- Local Presidents Conference Planning Committee Meeting 10/4/05, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  Facilitative correspondence; handwritten notes
- Local Presidents Conference Planning Committee Tom Anapolis Meeting 4/14/05, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  2005 New Local Presidents' timeline; program; flyer re conference; letters of invitation; related correspondence. See also New Local Presidents
- Local Presidents Conference Summary April 6-7, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  Summary of responses to questions re testing requirements, other issues
- Local Presidents Conference Meeting 3/4/05, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  Facilitative correspondence
- Local Presidents Conference Planning Committee 11/12/04, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  Agenda; tentative schedule for NYSUT Pre-RA Local and Retiree Council Presidents' Conference, April 6-7, 2005; program for Pre-Representative Assembly NYSUT Local Presidents' Conference, March 23-25, 2004; 2004 Local Presidents' Conference Evaluation Form
- Local Presidents Conference Planning Committee Meeting 12/17/03, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  Agenda; tentative schedule for NYSUT Pre-RA Local Presidents' Conference, March 24-25, 2004; Newsweek column, "A New Kind of Poverty," by Anna Quindlen, December 1, 2003; memos; evaluations from 2003 Local Presidents' Conference; related correspondence
- Local Presidents Survey K-12 Executive Summary 2004-2005 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  Draft executive summary
- Pre-RA Local Presidents Conference Planning Meeting 2/23/05, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  Agenda of 2005 Pre-RA Local and Retiree Council Presidents' Conference planning meeting of February 23, 2004; conference agenda; planning meeting minutes of December 15, 2004
- Pre-RA Local Presidents and Retiree Council Conference Planning Meeting 12/15/04, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  Local and Retiree Council Presidents' Conference program, April 6-7, 2005; conference planning meeting minutes of November 12, 2004
- Management Meeting 12/9/04, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  Agenda; materials re "Effective Teaching Program, NYSUT's Education and Learning Trust"; letter to local presidents re Education and Learning Trust, December 6, 2004; 2005 course catalog for Education and Learning Trust
- Managers Monthly Reports December 2005 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  Research Department manager's report
- Managers Monthly Reports November 2005 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  Educational Services Department manager's report; Research Department manager's report
- Managers Monthly Reports September 2005 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  School Finance and Policy Development progress report; Research Department manager's report; July/August monthly report for Education and Learning Trust
- Managers Monthly Reports August 2005 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  Educational Services Department manager's report
- Managers Monthly Reports July 2005 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  School Finance and Policy Development progress reports for July and August; Educational Services Department manager's report; Research Department manager's report
- Managers Monthly Reports June 2005 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  School Finance and Policy Development progress report; Educational Services Department manager's report; Research Department manager's report; monthly report for Education and Learning Trust
- Managers Monthly Reports May 2005 (Box 4, Folder 38)
- Managers Monthly Reports April 05, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  School Finance and Policy Development progress report; Educational Services Department manager's reports for March and April; Research Department manager's report
- Managers Monthly Reports March 2005 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  School Finance and Policy Development progress report
- Managers Monthly Reports January 2005 (Box 4, Folder 41)
- Managers Monthly Reports December 2004 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  School Finance and Policy Development progress report; monthly report for Education and Learning Trust
- Managers Monthly Reports November 2004 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  School Finance and Policy Development progress report; Research Department manager's report; monthly report for Education and Learning Trust
- Managers Monthly Reports October 2004 (Box 4, Folder 44)
- Managers Meeting 7/14/05, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  Memo reminder of meeting
- Managers Retreat June 7-8, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  Participant feedback sheets; text of welcoming remarks by first vice president Maria Neira, outlining objectives of the meeting; text of remarks by president Richard Ianuzzi, discussing mission statement, unification, changes in management titles; small group discussion items
- Managers Retreat Planning Committee Meeting 6/03/05, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  Memo from NYSUT president Richard Ianuzzi re management title changes, June 3, 2005; 2005 NYSUT Management list; 2005-2008 NYSUT Committees Officer Liaisons
- Managers Retreat Planning Committee Meeting 5/24/05, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  Proposed retreat agenda; minutes of Planning Committee meeting of May 11; agenda of Planning Committee meeting of May 4; possible questions for discussion; text of Maria Neira's and Richard Ianuzzi's remarks; small group discussion items
- Math League see NYS Math League
- Math Test Grades 4 and 8 Press Conference 10/6/04, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  Charts, graphs, and spreadsheets re elementary and middle-level mathematics in public schools, 1999-2004, district and school performance for intermediate-level mathematics; memo re press conference
- Mathematics and Science Partnership Grant Program see NCLB Mathematics and Science Partnership Grant Program
- Mathematics Standards Committee (SED) Grades 3-8 November 17, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  State Education Department Math Survey: Suggested NYSUT Response; report of the State Education Department Mathematics Standards Committee, October 27, 2005; request for public comment; agenda for NYSUT mathematics meeting, November 17, 2004; list of participants; draft survey questions for new math standards; presentation sheets re NYS's learning standards and grade 3-8 testing in English language arts and mathematics, fall 2004. See also James Kadamus Q&A Grades 3-8 Testing Program
- Mentor-Teacher Contract Language Search 2005 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  Document by NYSUT Research Department, Contract Language Search on Mentor/Teacher, listing text of contract language from South Lewis, Fredonia, Beaver River, Cazenovia, Harrison, South Glens Falls, Clarence, Fairport, Grand Island, Kenmore, and Hunter-Tannersville teachers associations
- Middle Level Education, 2004-2007 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  Preliminary draft of proposed amendments to sections 100.3 and 100.4 of Commissioner's Regulations relating to implementation of Middle-Level Strategy, April 29, 2005; ACT policy report, College Readiness Begins in Middle school, 2005; revised Strategy to Implement the Regents Policy Statement on Middle-Level Education, December 1, 2004; Report of the New York City Council Middle School Task Force, August 2007; Executive Summary, Breaking Ranks in the Middle: Strategies for Leading Middle Level Reform, by National Association of Secondary School Principals and the Education Alliance, Brown University; A Voice from the Middle: Highlights of the 2007 NASSP/PDK Middle School Student Poll; Regents discussion items, Public Reaction to Alternative Approaches to Implementation of the Regents Policy Statement on Middle-Level Education, January 7, 2004, and Strategy for Implementing the Regents Policy Statement on Middle-Level Education, February 6, 2004; State Education Department press release, "The New York State Education Department Announces Essential Elements: Schools-to-Watch Recognition Program," March 1, 2005
- Middle Level Liaisons Meeting 05/19/05, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  Agenda; materials from the May 20-21, 2004, meeting of Middle-Level Liaisons, October 4, 2004; Essential Elements of Standards-Focused Middle-Level Schools and Programs, revised 2003; Middle Level Rubric Development, by Learner-Centered Initiatives, Ltd., for Statewide Network of Middle Level Education Liaisons, May 21, 2004
- Middle Level: Hudson City Schools, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  Letter from Deputy Commissioner James Kadamus to James N. Baldwin, district superintendent of Rensselaer, Columbia and Greene Counties, re issues identified in Hudson City School District, including continued over-classification of black students as disabled, highest percentage of reported incidents of disruptive or violent behavior in the state, requesting meeting, July 1, 2005
- Middle Level Proposal, 2004-2005 (Box 4, Folder 55)
  Letter from State Education Chancellor Robert M. Bennett to NYSUT vice president Maria Neira re Three-Model Strategy to Implement the Regents Policy Statement on Middle-Level Education, specifically her concerns re Model C applications and ability of district superintendents to approve applications, March 2, 2005; memo from Maria Neira to NYSUT Board of Directors re her letter to Kadamus, continuing uncertainty over implementation of models, November 2, 2004; related memos
- Middle Level Education Lee Cutler October-November 2004 (Box 4, Folder 56)
  Letter from Maria Neira to Chancellor Robert M. Bennett re latest version of Middle-Level proposal, October 28, 2004; memos re Lee Cutler
- NAEP (National Assessment of Educational Progress) Science Report, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 57)
  "Less Than Proficient: A Review of the Draft Science Framework for the 2009 National Assessment of Educational Progress," by Paul R. Gross, October 24, 2005
- National Association of Latino Elected and Appointed Officials (NALEO) DC Summit 10/13/05, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 58)